<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
         xml:id="ch_org.cstudio.sns.jms2rdb">
<title>RDB Logging - org.cstudio.sns.jms2rdb</title>

<para>The plugin <code>org.cstudio.sns.jms2rdb</code> is a tool
that listens to JMS messages from the log, alarm system or other
CSS applications and sends them to the RDB.
</para>
<para>This tool uses an RDB schema for messages that extends the basic
schema described in <xref linkend="sec_msg_rdb_schema"/> by adding
the following commonly used message properties to the MESSAGE table itself:

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><code>TYPE</code>:
The message type, for example <quote>log</quote> or <quote>alarm</quote>.
</listitem>
<listitem><code>SEVERITY</code>:
The severity of the message, for example <quote>ERROR</quote> or <quote>MINOR</quote>.
</listitem>
<listitem><code>NAME</code>:
A name associated with the message. For <quote>log</quote> messages,
this is typically the name of the Java method that logged the information.
For <quote>alarm</quote> messages, this is the name of the Process Variable
that triggered the alarm.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<sect1>  <title>Relational Database Setup</title>
<para>The <filename>dbd</filename> sub-directory of the plugin sources
describes the RDB schema for MySQL, Oracle and PostgreSQL.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>  <title>Building the Tool</title>
<para>Use the <code>JMS2RDB.product</code> file to generate the binary.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>  <title>Running the Tool</title>
<para>You configure the connection parameters for JMS and your RDB
via a plugin customization file as described in <xref linkend="ch_preferences"/>.
Refer to the file <filename>plugin_customization.ini</filename>
included in the JMS2RDB plugin sources for an example.
</para>
<para>Once running, the JMS2RDB tool provides a web browser interface
as a basic status monitor under the URL
<programlisting>http://localhost:4913/main
</programlisting>
The port number can be adjusted in the preference settings of the tool.
To connect from another computer, replace <code>localhost</code> with
the name of the host that is executing the tool.
</para>

<figure xml:id="fig_jms2rdb">  <title>JMS-2-RDB Web Interface</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="jms2rdb.png" width="50%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>The main web page will look similar to <xref linkend="fig_jms2rdb"/>,
displaying the last message that was received and written to the RDB.
In case of errors, an addition <quote>Last Error</quote> section will display
for example the last database access error.
</para>

<para>To stop the tool, access the URL
<programlisting>http://localhost:4913/stop
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>
