<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:id="ch_chat">

<title>Chat - org.csstudio.utility.chat<indexterm><primary><code>org.csstudio.utility.chat</code></primary></indexterm></title>

<para>The Chat tool is a basic online group chat client for CSS.
The emphasis is on use in a control room context:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Easily log onto control room chat group.</listitem>
<listitem>Simply exchange screen-shots and files.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Technically, it is an XMPP chat protocol client
that can communicate with other clients that support
the same protocol (Pidgin, Google chat, Mac OS iChat, ...).
</para>

<figure xml:id="fig_chat">  <title>Chat Client (left) communicating with <quote>Pidgin</quote> (right)</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="chat.png" width="100%" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect1 xml:id="chat_usage"> <title>Basic Usage</title>
<para>Start the chat client from the menu <code>CSS</code>,
<code>Utilities</code>, <code>Group Chat</code>.
</para>
<para>The suggested user name that is initially displayed in the <code>Name:</code>
field of the chat tool is the name of the user logged onto the computer
suffixed by the network name of the computer.
The default password will be a dollar sign followed by the user name,
and the tool will attempt to create an account for that user and password
on the chat server.
The idea is that most users can simply press the <quote>Return</quote>
respectively <quote>Enter</quote> key in the user name field to log on
with the suggested user name and password.
Advanced users may enter a user name and password
that was registered with the chat server by other means.
</para>
<para>Once connected to the group chat, you can see other participants
who are connected to the chat in the <code>Participants</code> list.
Enter text to send in the <code>Send:</code> field, completing lines to
send with the <quote>Return</quote> key.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1> <title>Sending Files</title>
<para>By right-clicking on one of the entries
in the <code>Participants</code> list you can access
a context menu that allows you to <quote>Contact</quote>
another chat participant.
A separate chat panel will open for communicating with only that user,
outside of the group chat.
Note that the other participant will be asked if she accepts
the invitation to an individual chat, and may decline.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1> <title>Individual Chats</title>
<para>By right-clicking on one of the entries
in the <code>Participants</code> list you can access
a context menu with options <quote>Send File</quote>
and <quote>Send Screenshot</quote>.
When selecting to send a screen-shot, an image of your
current desktop will be sent to the receiver.
When sending a file, you will be prompted for the name
of the file that you want to send.
Note that in either case the receiving participant of the chat
will be asked if she accepts the file that you sent,
and may decline.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1> <title>XMPP Server Setup - Openfire</title>
<para>XMPP is an open technology for real-time communication.
More information can be found at
<link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org">http://xmpp.org</link>,
including lists of XMPP server implementations
and other chat clients compatible with XMPP.
</para>
<para><code>Openfire</code>, available from
<link xlink:href="http://www.igniterealtime.org/projects/openfire">http://www.igniterealtime.org/projects/openfire</link>,
is an open source, Java-based XMPP server
for Windows, Linux and Mac OS X.
For Windows, it includes an executable <filename>bin/openfire.exe</filename>
to start and stop the server and to access its web interface via
a <quote>Launch Admin</quote> button.
</para>
<para>When starting Openfire for the first time, you need
to configure the following via its web interface:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Domain - Set to either <code>localhost</code>
for initial tests on one computer, or set to the complete
and correct host name.
</listitem>
<listitem>Database - Selecting the <quote>embedded</quote>
database seems to work fine.
</listitem>
<listitem>Administrator account - Use for example <quote>admin@localhost</quote>
and a password of your choice.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>From now on, to log into the admin web interface of Openfire,
you have to use just <quote>admin</quote> and the password that you configured,
<emphasis role="strong">not</emphasis> <quote>admin@localhost</quote>!
</para>

<para>In the Openfire online admin interface you should check
the setting under <quote>Server</quote>, <quote>Server Settings</quote>,
<quote>Registration &amp; Login</quote>.
By default, users should be allowed to automatically create new accounts.
The CSS chat client will use this option to attempt automatic account
creation with the suggested user name and password as described in
<xref linkend="chat_usage"/>.
If you choose to disable automated account creation, you need to create
user accounts in the Openfire admin interface.
</para>

<para>The CSS chat client expects to connect to a chat room
called <quote>css</quote>.
From the Openfire online admin interface,
select the <quote>Group Chat</quote> tab.
Press <quote>Create New Room</quote>:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Enter <code>css</code> as the room ID.</listitem>
<listitem>You will also need to enter a room name, description
and topic, which you can all set to <quote>CSS</quote>.
</listitem>
<listitem>Under <code>Show Real JIDs of Occupants to:</code>,
select <quote>Anyone</quote>.
This will allow the chat clients to directly contact
chat group participants for individual chats and file
exchange.
</listitem>
<listitem>Before you save the room settings, take note
of the full name of the group chat.
It should use the chat room ID followed by <code>@conference</code>
and the host name of the server, similar to
<programlisting>css@conference.localhost
</programlisting>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>To reset the Openfire configuration, 
for example after forgetting the admin password,
stop openfire. In the file <filename>conf/openfire.xml</filename>,
locate the <code>setup</code> entry. Set it to <code>false</code>,
start Openfire again and when you now access the admin web interface,
you can configure a new admin password.
</para>
</sect1>


<sect1> <title>Chat Client Settings</title>
<para>The CSS chat clients has the following preference settings:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>chat_server - Host name that runs the chat server,
for example <quote>localhost</quote>.
</listitem>
<listitem>group - Name of the chat group to join,
for example <quote>css@conference.localhost</quote>.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>


<sect1> <title>Example using Pidgin</title>
<para>Pidgin, available from
<link xlink:href="http://pidgin.im">http://pidgin.im</link>,
is an open-source chat client for various operating systems
that can be used to test an XMPP server setup.
</para>
<para>To configure Pidgin for a connection with Openfire,
use the Pidgin menu bar to create an account with the following
settings:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Procotol - XMPP</listitem>
<listitem>Username, password - Either enter a name and password
that has already been added to Openfire,
or enter a new name and password with the option
to <quote>Create this new account on server</quote>.
</listitem>
<listitem>Domain - Enter name of XMPP server host, for example <quote>localhost</quote>.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>In the <quote>Advanced</quote> account setup panel,
check that the XMPP connect port is set to 5222
and the file transfer proxies is set to the host name
of your XMPP server port 7777, for example
<code>localhost:7777</code>.
</para>

</sect1>







</chapter>