<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
      
      

      

<info>
<title>Control System Studio</title>
<subtitle>What you always wanted to know but were afraid to ask</subtitle>
<author><firstname>Kay</firstname><surname>Kasemir</surname></author>
<copyright><year>2011</year><holder>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</holder></copyright>
</info>


<preface>  <title>No Warranty</title>
<para>
Although the programs and procedures described in this book are meant to be helpful instruments for
building a control system, there is no warranty, either expressed or implied, including, but not limited to,
fitness for a particular purpose.
The entire risk as to the quality and performance of the programs and procedures is with you.
Should the programs or procedures prove defective, you assume the cost of all necessary servicing, repair or correction.
In no event will anybody be liable to you for damages, including any general, special, incidental or consequential damages
arising out of the use or inability to use the computer programs and procedures described in here
(including but not limited to loss of data or data being rendered inaccurate or losses sustained by you or third parties
or a failure of the programs described in here to operate with any other programs).
</para>
</preface>

<acknowledgements>
<para>
Control System Studio (CSS) is the result of contributions from many people:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>First of all, CSS builds heavily on Eclipse.</listitem>
<listitem>Matthias Clausen at the Deutsches Electronen Synchrotron started the CSS idea.</listitem>
<listitem>Many people from the Canadian Light Source, Brookhaven National Laboratory, Argonne National Laboratory, ITER and other
sites have contributed either through extensions, code fixes, suggestions or bug reports.
Check the <code>@author</code> tags in the source code to get an idea.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>The sources for this book are on SourceForge under
<link xlink:href="http://cs-studio.hg.sourceforge.net/hgweb/cs-studio/docbook/">http://cs-studio.hg.sourceforge.net/hgweb/cs-studio/docbook/</link>.
</para>
<para>Thanks to Gabriele Carcassi, the latest HTML version is available at
<link xlink:href="http://cs-studio.sourceforge.net/docbook/">http://cs-studio.sourceforge.net/docbook/</link>,
and the current PDF is at
<link xlink:href="http://cs-studio.sourceforge.net/docbook/css_book.pdf">http://cs-studio.sourceforge.net/docbook/css_book.pdf</link>.
</para>
</acknowledgements>

<part>
<title>CSS Guide</title>
<partintro>
<para>This book has two parts.
The first part consists of an introduction to CSS.
It explains how to compile CSS from sources,
how to install it, how to perform the initial setup
of the archive and alarm system.
It is meant to serve as a guide for those who need
to install, maintain and extend CSS.
</para>
<para>The second part of the book has reference chapters
for selected plugins.
</para>
</partintro>

<!-- 
* Installing, configuring, running CSS
 Starting with MySQL, JMS, Java, Eclipse and the CSS sources,
 how to build the Archive Engine, Alarm Server, CSS GUI.
 How to configure them.
 How to run the archive engine.
 How to tweak CSS for your site's end users.
 How to run the alarm server.
 (1-2 days)

* Basic CSS/Eclipse usage (half day)
 Data Browser, EPICS PV tree, ...

* BOY (Maybe 1 day)

* Alarm Handler (half day)
 -->

<xi:include href="introduction.xml" />

<xi:include href="css_intro/introduction.xml" />
<xi:include href="compiling/compiling.xml" />
<xi:include href="preferences.xml" />

<xi:include href="archive/archive.xml" />

<xi:include href="data.xml" />

<xi:include href="data_exchange.xml" />
</part>

<part>
<title>Plug-in Reference</title>
<partintro>
<para>The following chapters contain references for certain
CSS plugins.
</para>
</partintro>

<xi:include href="org.csstudio.core.feature/chapter.xml" />
<xi:include href="org.csstudio.core.util.feature/chapter.xml" />
<xi:include href="org.csstudio.ui.menu/chapter.xml" />

<xi:include href="org.csstudio.archive.engine/chapter.xml" />
</part>

<!-- Appendices -->
<xi:include href="docbook.xml" /> 

<!-- Index, populated by translator -->
<index></index>

</book>
